<bathroom>	<objects>		<Obj>Bath</Obj>		<Descr>The ceramic bath contains beryllium, obtained from the mineral beryl. Tellurium sometimes is used to make ceramics.</Descr>		<Symbol>Be, Te</Symbol>		<Names>beryllium, tellurium</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Toilet</Obj>		<Descr>The ceramic toilet bowl contains beryllium, obtained from the mineral beryl. Tellurium sometimes is used to make ceramics.</Descr>		<Symbol>Be, Te</Symbol>		<Names>beryllium, tellurium</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Tiles</Obj>		<Descr>The ceramic floor tiles contain beryllium, obtained from the mineral beryl. Tellurium sometimes is used to make ceramics.</Descr>		<Symbol>Be, Te</Symbol>		<Names>beryllium, tellurium</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Soap</Obj>		<Descr>Soap is made from animal fats and alkalis, and contains sodium.</Descr>		<Symbol>Na</Symbol>		<Names>Sodium</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Taps</Obj>		<Descr>Taps are made of iron that may come from hematite; nickel extracted from pentlandite, and chromium  from the mineral chromite.</Descr>		<Symbol>Cr, Fe, Ni</Symbol>		<Names>chromium, iron, nickel</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Mirror</Obj>		<Descr>Mirrors are made from glass which can contain silicon, sodium, magnesium and aluminium. The mirror could be backed with silver or aluminium.</Descr>		<Symbol>Si, Na, Mg, Al, Ag</Symbol>		<Names>silicon, sodium, magnesium, aluminium, silver</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Cleaner</Obj>		<Descr>The abrasive part of this cleanser is silica, which contains silicon.</Descr>		<Symbol>Si</Symbol>		<Names>Silicon</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Watch</Obj>		<Descr>Watches contain silicon, copper, chromium, iron, nickel, silver, mercury, zinc, lead, tin and gold.</Descr>		<Symbol>Si, Cu, Cr, Fe, Ni, Ag, Hg, Pb, Sn, Zn, Au</Symbol>		<Names>silicon, copper, chromium, iron, nickel, silver, mercury, lead, tin, zinc, gold</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Toothpaste</Obj>		<Descr>Toothpaste contains titanium dioxide, which comes from the minerals rutile, ilmenite and anatase. Silica and aluminium dioxide are added to help scrape away plaque. And fluoride toothpastes usually contain either calcium fluoride from the element fluorite, or tin fluoride. Some toothpaste tubes are made from aluminium, which comes from the mineral bauxite.</Descr>		<Symbol>Al, Ca, Si, Sn, Ti, F</Symbol>		<Names>aluminium, calcium, silicon, tin, titanium, fluorine</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Talcum</Obj>		<Descr>Talcum powder is a purified form of magnesium silicate obtained from the mineral talc.</Descr>		<Symbol>Ca, Mg, Si</Symbol>		<Names>calcium, magnesium, silicon</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Glass</Obj>		<Descr>Glass is made from silicon, found in the mineral silica.</Descr>		<Symbol>Si</Symbol>		<Names>Silicon</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Cosmetics</Obj>		<Descr>Among a wide range of other ingredients, cosmetics contain titanium dioxide from rutile, ilmenite and anatase, iron, silicon from silica, magnesium from talc (magnesium silicate hydroxide), and zinc from minerals such as sphalerite. Ground mica containing silicon is added to cosmetics to add sparkle.</Descr>		<Symbol>Fe, Mg, Si, Ti, Zn</Symbol>		<Names>iron, magnesium, silicon, titanium, zinc</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Deodorant</Obj>		<Descr>The antiperspirant agents in deodorants contain aluminium and zirconium.</Descr>		<Symbol>Al, Zr</Symbol>		<Names>aluminium, zirconium</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Hairdryer</Obj>		<Descr>The hot air from a hair dryer is produced when air from the fan passes over a coiled nichrome wire that is wrapped around insulating mica boards. Nichrome is an alloy of nickel and chromium. Silicon is the main metal found in mica.</Descr>		<Symbol>Cr, Ni, Si</Symbol>		<Names>chromium, nickel, silicon</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Shampoo</Obj>		<Descr>The main anti-dandruff agents in this type of shampoo are zinc from minerals such as sphalerite, and selenium.</Descr>		<Symbol>Se, Zn</Symbol>		<Names>selenium, zinc</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Doorknob</Obj>		<Descr>The doorknob is made of brass - an alloy of copper and zinc.</Descr>		<Symbol>Cu, Zn</Symbol>		<Names>copper, zinc</Names>	</objects></bathroom>