<bedroom>	<objects>		<Obj>Computer</Obj>		<Descr>Computers contain gold, silica, zinc, aluminium, nickel, iron and about thirty other minerals. The nickel comes from pentlandite, aluminium from bauxite, iron from minerals such as hematite and limonite, and zinc from minerals such as sphalerite. The electrical wiring is made of copper obtained from minerals such as chalcopyrite. Gallium and germanium are part of transistors. Lead lines the glass of the monitor to shield radiation. Some of the other elements found in very small amounts in the electronic components in computers are niobium, palladium, platinum, rhodium, ruthenium, selenium, tantalum terbium, titanium, vanadium and yttrium. Arsenic is found in the laser in a CD burner.</Descr>		<Symbol>Al, As, Au, Ba, Cu, Fe, Ga, Ge, In, Nb, Ni, Pb, Pd, Pt, Rh, Ru, Se, Si, Ta, Tb, Ti, V, Y, Zn</Symbol>		<Names>aluminium, arsenic, gold, barium, copper, iron, gallium, germanium, indium, niobium, nickel, lead, palladium, platinum, rhodium, ruthenium, selenium, silicon, tantalum, terbium, titanium, vanadium, yttrium, zinc</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Cymbals</Obj>		<Descr>Brass, an alloy of copper and zinc.</Descr>		<Symbol>Cu, Zn</Symbol>		<Names>copper, zinc</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Lamp</Obj>		<Descr>The light globe will contain glass – made from silica (Si), soda ash (Na), lime (Ca), coal and salt. The filament is tungsten. The wires into the filament contain copper and nickel. Molybdenum wires support the lead-in wires. The wires in the glass are made of a combination of nickel-iron alloy with a copper sleeve. There is a fuse made of nickel, manganese, copper and/or silicon alloys. The base is made of brass (Cu and Zn).If the globe is fluorescent it will contain Beryllium and germanium. Hafmium is used in incandescent lamps.</Descr>		<Symbol>Si, Na, Ca, C, W, Cu, Ni, Mo, Mn, Zn, Be, Ge, Hf</Symbol>		<Names>silicon, sodium, calcium, carbon, tungsten, copper, nickel, molybdenum, manganese, zinc, beryllium, germanium, hafmium</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Television</Obj>		<Descr>The picture tube contains a coating of lead on the inside to protects viewers from radiation. Lead is obtained mainly from galena. The circuit boards in a TV set contain gold, silica, zinc, aluminium, nickel, iron and about thirty other minerals. The nickel comes from pentlandite, aluminium from bauxite, iron from minerals such as hematite and limonite, and zinc from minerals such as sphalerite. The electrical wiring is made of copper obtained from minerals such as chalcopyrite. Some of the other elements found in very small amounts in the electronic components in television sets are niobium, palladium, platinum, rhodium, ruthenium, selenium, tantalum terbium, titanium, vanadium and yttrium. Strontium is used to make the glass in television tubes.</Descr>		<Symbol>Al, Au, Ba, Cs, Cu, Fe, Ga, Ge, In, Nb, Ni, Pb, Pd, Pt, Rb, Rh, Ru, Se, Si, Sr, Ta, Tb, Ti, V, Y, Zn</Symbol>		<Names>aluminium, gold, barium, caesium, copper, iron, gallium, germanium, indium, niobium, nickel, lead, palladium, platinum, rubidium, rhodium, ruthenium, selenium, silicon, strontium, tantalum, terbium, titanium, vanadium, yttrium, zinc</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Golf clubs</Obj>		<Descr>Golf clubs contain aluminium from bauxite, and titanium from rutile.</Descr>		<Symbol>Al, Ti</Symbol>		<Names>aluminium, titanium</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Poster on wall</Obj>		<Descr>Printing ink can contain cobalt extracted from cobaltite, manganese from minerals such as pyrolusite, and cerium which belongs to the rare earth elements group and is found in minerals contained in pegmatites.</Descr>		<Symbol>Ce, Co, Mn</Symbol>		<Names>cerium, cobalt, manganese</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Medals</Obj>		<Descr>Medals typically are gold, silver and bronze. Silver comes from the mineral galena. Bronze is a mixture of copper and tin. Tin comes from the mineral cassiterite, an oxide of tin. Copper is extracted from its sulphide ores.</Descr>		<Symbol>Ag, Au, Cu, Sn</Symbol>		<Names>silver, gold, copper, tin</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Stereo</Obj>		<Descr>Within the stereo are gold, iron from minerals such as hematite and limonite, and nickel obtained from pentlandite. The wiring contains copper, mainly from the Copper sulphides chalcopyrite or chalcosite. Speakers have a magnet containing iron. Arsenic is found in the laser in the CD player.</Descr>		<Symbol>As, Au, Cu, Fe, Ni</Symbol>		<Names>arsenic, gold, copper, iron, nickel</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Computer monitor</Obj>		<Descr>The computer monitor contains a coating of lead on the inside to protects viewers from radiation. Lead is obtained mainly from galena. The circuit boards in the monitor contain gold, silica, zinc, aluminium, nickel, iron and about thirty other minerals. The nickel comes from pentlandite, aluminium from bauxite, iron from minerals such as hematite and limonite, and zinc from minerals such as sphalerite. The electrical wiring is made of copper obtained from minerals such as chalcopyrite. Some of the other elements found in very small amounts in are niobium, palladium, platinum, rhodium, ruthenium, selenium, tantalum terbium, titanium, vanadium and yttrium. Strontium is used to make the glass in the monitor.</Descr>		<Symbol>Al, Au, Ba, Cu, Fe, Ga, Ge, In, Nb, Ni, Pb, Pd, Pt, Rh, Ru, Se, Si, Sr, Ta, Tb, Ti, V, Y, Zn</Symbol>		<Names>aluminium, gold, barium, copper, iron, gallium, germanium, indium, niobium, nickel, lead, palladium, platinum, rhodium, ruthenium, selenium, silicon, strontium, tantalum, terbium, titanium, vanadium, yttrium, zinc</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Weights</Obj>		<Descr>These weights are made from iron. Iron is obtained from minerals such as hematite and limonite.</Descr>		<Symbol>Fe</Symbol>		<Names>iron</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Fan</Obj>		<Descr>The blades of this fan are made of steel, which consists of iron mixed with a number of other elements such as carbon, copper, manganese, phosphorus and silicon. Iron is obtained from minerals such as hematite and limonite.</Descr>		<Symbol>Fe, C, Cu, Mn, P, Si</Symbol>		<Names>iron, carbon, copper, manganese, phosphorus, silicon</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Baseball bat</Obj>		<Descr>Scandium increases the strength and durability of baseball bats. It also increases their flexibility, and resistance to fatigue.</Descr>		<Symbol>Sc</Symbol>		<Names>scandium</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Drum kit</Obj>		<Descr>Paint contains titanium dioxide - from ilmenite. Rods and frame are chrome plated steel, with brass threaded tension rods.</Descr>		<Symbol>Ti, Cu, Zn, Cr</Symbol>		<Names>titanium, copper, zinc, chromium</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Chair</Obj>		<Descr>The chair is partly made of chromium-plated steel.</Descr>		<Symbol>Ni, Cr, Ti, Fe</Symbol>		<Names>nickel, chromium, titanium, iron</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Dumbbells</Obj>		<Descr>These weights are made of steel, which consists of iron mixed with a number of other elements such as carbon, copper, manganese, phosphorus and silicon.</Descr>		<Symbol>Fe, C, Cu, Mn, P, Cr</Symbol>		<Names>iron, carbon, copper, manganese, phosphorus, chromium</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Mirror</Obj>		<Descr>Mirrors are made from glass which can contain silicon, sodium, magnesium and aluminium. The mirror could be backed with silver or aluminium.</Descr>		<Symbol>Si, Na, Mg, Al, Ag</Symbol>		<Names>silicon, sodium, magnesium, aluminium, silver</Names>	</objects></bedroom>