<elementlist><element><name>Hydrogen H</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Helium He</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Lithium Li</name><use><![CDATA[The biggest use of lithium compounds is to make glass, ceramics, and aluminium.Lithium is used to make synthetic rubber, greases and other lubricants.It is used to make newer types of rechargeable batteries.Lithium mixed with other light-weight metals, such as aluminium and magnesium, forms strong, light-weight alloys.Some lithium, in the form of lithium carbonate or lithium citrate, is used as a medicine to treat gout (an inflammation of joints), and to treat serious mental illness.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Some lithium is recovered from the mineral spodumene. Commercial quantities of spodumene are in igneous rock deposits which have cooled very slowly allowing large crystals to form.Most lithium is recovered from brine (water saturated with salt), or water with a high concentration of lithium carbonate. Brines trapped in the earth's crust are the major source of lithium carbonate. These sources are less expensive to mine than those from rock, such as spodumene, petalite, and other lithium-bearing minerals.]]></geology></element><element><name>Beryllium Be</name><use><![CDATA[It is commonly alloyed with nickel for use in springs, electrodes and non-sparking tools. Alloyed with copper gives a hard strong alloy with high resistance to wear and is used in gyroscopes, computer parts, and instruments that need lightness and strength. Other alloys are used as a structural material for high performance aircraft, missiles, spacecraft (such as the USA space shuttle), and communication satellites. It is a common component of ceramics.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Beryllium is found in a number of minerals. The most important mineral is beryl, Be<font size="10">3</font>Al<font size="10">2</font>(SiO<font size="10">3</font>)<font size="10">6</font>, which is often found as hexagonal prisms. Aquamarine and emerald are precious forms of beryl.]]></geology></element><element><name>Boron B</name><use><![CDATA[Borax Na<font size="10">2</font>B<font size="10">4</font>O<font size="10">7</font>.10H<font size="10">2</font>O is used as a water softener in washing powders and boron compounds are used in production of enamels for covering steel of refrigerators and washing machines.. Boron compounds are also extensively used in the manufacture of borosilicate glasses. Boron filaments, a high-strength, lightweight material, are used for advanced aerospace structures and in fibre optics, . Boron as Boric acid is also used in household insecticides to control cockroaches, silverfish, ants, fleas, and other insects.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Boron is not found free in nature. It occurs usually as orthoboric acid in some volcanic spring waters and as borates in borax and colemanite.]]></geology></element><element><name>Carbon C</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Nitrogen N</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Oxygen O</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Fluorine F</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Neon Ne</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Sodium Na</name><use><![CDATA[Sodium metal is used in the preparation of lead compounds that were used as an anti-knock reagent in leaded petrol.Sodium is a reagent in the manufacture of other chemical products because it is a good reducing agent.Sodium compounds like table salt (sodium chloride, NaCl), soda ash (sodium carbonate, Na<font size="10">2</fontCO<font size="10">3</font>), baking soda (sodium bicarbonate, NaHCO<font size="10">3</font>, bicarb), and caustic soda (sodium hydroxide, NaOH), are important to the paper, glass, soap, textile, petroleum, chemical, and metal industries Sodium vapour is used in lamps for street lighting.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Sodium is never found as the free element in nature as it is so reactive, however sodium is the sixth most abundant element in the earth's crust. The most common sodium containing mineral is rock salt (sodium chloride, NaCl, or halite), but it occurs in many other minerals including sodium borate (borax), sodium carbonate (soda), sodium nitrate (Chile saltpetre), and sodium sulphate (thenardite).]]></geology></element><element><name>Magnesium Mg</name><use><![CDATA[The greatest demand for Magnesium is for the production of alloys which are strong, light and corrosion resistant for use in aircraft, car engines, and missiles.Magnesium is also used in flares and fireworks as it produces a bright, white light when burnt.Magnesium is used as a reducing agent for the production of uranium and other metals.The hydroxide (milk of magnesia), chloride, sulphate (Epsom salts), and the citrate of magnesium are all used in medicine.Magnesium oxide is used as bricks and liners in furnaces.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Although magnesium is the eighth most abundant element in the earth's crust, it is never found in the free metal form.Magnesite (MgCO<font size="10">3</font>), the main ore of magnesium, occurs as vein deposits, or as nodules that range in size from 1mm to 100cm. Magnesite is commonly associated with serpentinite.Magnesium also occurs in dolomite (CaMg(CO<font size="10">3</font>)<font size="10">2</font>.]]></geology></element><element><name>Aluminium Al</name><use><![CDATA[Aluminium is a silvery-white metal with a low density, high electrical and heat conductivity, corrosion resistance, and good malleability (ability to be shaped). As an alloy it can make strong materials.Aluminium has a wide range of common uses. Many kitchen items (pots and pans, foil, dishes) are made of aluminium. The transportation industry uses large amounts of aluminium in cars, trucks, boats, aircraft, and aircraft engines. Road signs and high-voltage power lines are made mostly of aluminium.It is commonly used in packaging, electrical goods, and in light-weight structures in the building industry.Small amounts of aluminium are used as abrasives, refractories (materials that retain their shape under high temperature), and in water treatment, antiperspirants, and bread-making (where it helps the bread to rise).]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Aluminium is not found in the free metal form.Bauxite, the most important ore of aluminium, is produced by weathering of volcanic rocks during the formation of soil in tropical and sub-tropical climates.Australia produces about 40% of the world's bauxite. It is found mainly on Queensland's Cape York Peninsula, the Darling Range in south-west Western Australia, and at Gove in the Northern Territory.Guinea also has large bauxite deposits. Brazil, Jamaica, China and India also have bauxite deposits.]]></geology></element><element><name>Silicon Si</name><use><![CDATA[Silica, as sand, is a principal ingredient of glass, a material with excellent mechanical, optical, thermal, and electrical properties. It is used in the manufacture of computer chips, lubricants, and concrete and bricks. Doped with boron, gallium, phosphorus, or arsenic, silicon is used in transistors, solar cells, rectifiers, and other electronic solid-state devices.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Silicon is not found free in nature, but occurs chiefly as the oxide, and as silicates. Sand, quartz, rock crystal, amethyst, agate, flint, jasper, and opal are all silicon oxides. Granite, hornblende, asbestos, feldspar, clay, mica are a few of the many silicate minerals. Silicon makes up 25.7% of the earth's crust by weight and is the second most abundant element in the earth's crust.]]></geology></element><element><name>Phosphorus P</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Sulphur S</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Chlorine Cl</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Argon Ar</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Potassium K</name><use><![CDATA[Most commonly potassium is used in fertilizers - usually as the chloride, sulphate, nitrate, or carbonate form; fireworks (potassium nitrate, KNO<font size="10">3</font>, and potassium chlorate, KClO<font size="10">3</font>), and liquid detergents (potassium phosphates).]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Potassium metal is far too reactive to be found uncombined in nature but the element is quite abundant in the earth's crust. Potassium is found extensively as potash (KOH) and is mined in Germany, USA, and elsewhere from minerals such as sylvite (KCl), carnallite, and langbeinite, from ancient lake and sea beds.]]></geology></element><element><name>Calcium Ca</name><use><![CDATA[Calcium is used as a reducing agent in the manufacture of metals such as thorium, uranium and zirconium and alloys with other metals like aluminium, beryllium, copper, lead, and magnesium for some useful applications. It is a 'getter' for residual gases in vacuum tubes.The greatest use is in the manufacture of quicklime (CaO) and cement.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Calcium metal is never found as the free metal in nature, however, calcium is the fifth most abundant element in the earth's crust. It is mined mainly from limestone (CaCO<font size="10">3</font>), gypsum (CaSO<font size="10">4</font>.2H<font size="10">2</font>O), and fluorite (CaF<font size="10">2</font>) deposits.]]></geology></element><element><name>Scandium Sc</name><use><![CDATA[Scandium is used in mercury vapour lamps to create a light that is very much like natural sunlight. This type of lighting is used in photography and television.Scandium is used to make crystals for laser research. It also is used in the aerospace industry.An alloy of scandium and aluminium is used to make lightweight, strong sporting equipment such as baseball bats, bicycle frames, and lacrosse sticks.Scandium can be alloyed with titanium to make a strong, heat-resistant metal alloy.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Scandium is never found in the free metal form.It is usually found in uranium minerals, although very small amounts occur in rocks rich in iron or magnesium.Scandium is a much more abundant element in the sun and some stars than on earth.Most scandium is recovered from thortveitite, or is extracted as a by-product from uranium production plants.]]></geology></element><element><name>Titanium Ti</name><use><![CDATA[The most important use of titanium is as a pigment. As the whitest substance known, titanium oxide is used as a whitener in paints, sugar, sweets, toothpaste.The aerospace industry uses alloys of titanium in airframes and engines. Titanium frames for sunglasses and sports equipment containing titanium are sought after because they are so light and strong.Titanium is non-reactive, non-toxic and corrosion resistant, making it perfect for use in replacement hip joints, pace makers and pins for bone repair.Because titanium paint is an excellent reflector of infrared radiation, it is used in solar observatories where heat causes poor viewing conditions.Star sapphires and rubies exhibit their star-like light properties because of the presence of titanium oxide (TiO<font size="10">2</font>).]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Titanium metal is not found in the free element form.It is found in the minerals rutile (TiO<font size="10">2</font>), ilmenite (FeTiO<font size="10">3</font>), and sphene. It also is present in titanates, in many iron ores, and in many igneous rocks.When rutile and ilmenite are present in sediments from igneous rocks, they are called 'heavy minerals'. These are an important source of titanium.Australia is a world leader in the production of mineral sands. Other major producers are South Africa, North America, Canada, Scandinavia, and Malaysia.]]></geology></element><element><name>Vanadium V</name><use><![CDATA[Vanadium is used to produce rust-resistant springs and steel tools. Its strength and radioactive properties make it useful in nuclear applications.About 80% of the vanadium produced is used to strengthen steel.Vanadium foil is used to bind titanium to steel. Vanadium pentoxide (V<font size="10">2</font>O<font size="10">5</font>) is used in ceramics and as a chemical catalyst.Vanadium compounds are used for dyeing and printing fabrics.A mixture of vanadium and gallium is used to produce superconductive magnets.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Vanadium is not found in the free metal form in nature. However, it is found in many minerals, the most important being carnotite and vanadinite [3Pb<font size="10">3</font>(VO<font size="10">4</font>)<font size="10">2</font>.PbCl<font size="10">2</font>]. It is also present in some crude oils.Vanadium is a trace element in a number of different rocks, and is a by-product of some mining operations. Vanadium is found in magnetite (iron oxide) deposits that are also very rich in titanium. It is also found in bauxite (aluminium ore), in rocks with high concentrations of phosphorus-containing minerals, and sandstones with a high uranium content.Vanadium is also recovered from carbon-rich deposits such as coal, oil shale, crude oil, and tar sands.]]></geology></element><element><name>Chromium Cr</name><use><![CDATA[Chromium is used to harden steel, to manufacture stainless steel, and to form alloys. Stainless steel production consumes most of the chromium produced annually. Chromium is also used to make heat-resisting steel. Some alloys that use chromium have military applications.In plating, chromium produces a hard, beautiful surface that resists corrosion.Chromium is used by the aircraft and other industries to anodise aluminium and it can also be used as a catalyst.It gives glass an emerald green colour. It is responsible for the green colour of emeralds and the red colour of rubies.Compounds of chromium are used as pigments, as oxidising agents and in the textile industry to fix colours in the cloth.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Chromium is not found in the free metal form in nature.The most important ore is chromite (FeCr<font size="10">2</font>O<font size="10">4</font>), which is found in Turkey, USA, South Africa, Albania, Finland, Iran, Madagascar, Russia, Southern Rhodesia, Transvaal, Cuba, Brazil, Japan, India, Pakistan, and the Philippines.When certain types of magma cool slowly deep inside the earth's crust, chromite crystals are precipitated. Because of their high density, they fall to the bottom where they are concentrated in layers.Chromite is also found in metamorphic rocks such as serpentites.]]></geology></element><element><name>Manganese Mn</name><use><![CDATA[Steel becomes harder when it is alloyed with manganese. Hardened steel is important in the manufacture of construction materials like beams (24% of manganese used), machinery (14% of manganese used), and cars and planes (13% of manganese used).Manganese by itself colours glass an amethyst colour, and is responsible for the purple colour of amethyst. It is used to colour bricks and ceramic tiles.Manganese is used in the preparation of oxygen and chlorine.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Manganese is not found in the free metal form in nature. However, manganese minerals consisting of oxides, silicates, and carbonates, are common.Sedimentary manganese forms in shallow, marine sedimentary basins. Manganese precipitation usually happens where seawater without much oxygen meets oxygenated surface waters.Pyrolusite (MnO<font size="10">2</font>) is an oxidation product of weathered manganese minerals. Like bauxite, it is found in the tropics where high rainfall and weathering of rocks are common.Manganese nodules on ocean floors contain about 24% manganese.Most manganese comes from ores in Australia, Brazil, Gabon, India, Russia, and South Africa.]]></geology></element><element><name>Iron Fe</name><use><![CDATA[Iron is cheap and very abundant so it is used for many different things from nails and hammers to bridges and engine blocks. However, pure iron is soft and rusts readily so it needs to be made into steel by adding small amounts or carbon and other metals to make it stronger and more durable. Steel is used to make railway tracks, roofing, fencing, pumps and cranes, food containers, pipes and washing machines. Iron with only a little carbon in it is called 'wrought iron'. It is easily shaped and is used for ornamental work for gates and garden furniture.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Haematite, Fe<font size="10">2</font>O<font size="10">3</font>, is found throughout the world and is the most important ore of iron. Most of the world's important iron ore resources occur in iron-rich sedimentary rocks known as banded iron formations that are greater than 600 million years old. These deposits occur on all continents. In Australia the major source of iron ore is in the Hamersley Province in Western Australia.]]></geology></element><element><name>Cobalt Co</name><use><![CDATA[Cobalt has been used for centuries to create beautiful deep blue glass, ceramics, pottery and tiles. It is also used to make paint pigments.Cobalt is used in a number of industrial applications. When alloyed with other metals, cobalt creates very strong magnets. Superalloys (those developed for use at high temperatures and under stress) containing cobalt are used in jet engines and gas turbine engines. These superalloys account for nearly half of the cobalt used each year.Some cobalt is used to make cutting and wear-resistant materials.A synthetic isotope of cobalt, cobalt-60, produces gamma rays. This isotope is used to sterilise medical supplies and foods, for industrial testing, and to fight cancer.Vitamin B12 contains cobalt. In areas where there is little cobalt in the soil, farmers provide salt blocks containing cobalt for their animals to lick to get enough cobalt into their diet to allow them to produce this vitamin.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Cobalt is not found in the free metal form in nature.All cobalt is obtained as a by-product of the mining of other elements, such as copper. Canada, Morocco, and Zaire are the biggest producers of cobalt.Meteorites often contain cobalt.The ocean floor has nodules of metals that form when hot water from deep in the earth comes into contact with the cold ocean water. Because these nodules are mostly manganese they are called manganese nodules. It is estimated that there are millions of tons of cobalt in these nodules. Presently, we do not have the technology to retrieve these nodules at a reasonable cost.]]></geology></element><element><name>Nickel Ni</name><use><![CDATA[More than 80% of the world's nickel production is used in alloys. At least 3000 alloys of nickel have been identified. Stainless steel is the most popular alloy because of its strength and corrosion resistance. Stainless steel, which contains mainly chromium and nickel, is used in motor vehicles, tools, cutlery, and the chemical and building industries.Specialty steels and alloys are used in pipelines, aircraft, vehicles and buildings.Nickel-copper alloys are used for marine components and desalination plants.Nickel-chromium alloys are used in jet engines, high temperature reaction vessels, and for the storage of liquefied gases.Other uses of nickel include electroplating, ceramics, batteries, coins, glass pigments, electronics and as catalysts.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[The main nickel ore is pentlandite which forms when heavy crystallised minerals settle out from magma and become concentrated.Currently all Australia's nickel production is from Western Australia.]]></geology></element><element><name>Copper Cu</name><use><![CDATA[Copper is an excellent electrical conductor so it is widely used in electrical generators, motors, power and lighting fixtures and electrical appliances. It is also an excellent heat conductor so it is used for thin-walled tubing in air-conditioning and refrigeration units, car radiators, hot water services and home heating. Jewellery, cooking pots, coins and medals are created from copper. Copper can also be alloyed with other metals such as zinc and tin to make alloys such as brass and bronze.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Copper is found as the pure metal but more common forms are sulfide minerals such as chalcopyrite (CuFeS<font size="10">2</font>), Bornite (Cu<font size="10">5</font>FeS<font size="10">4</font>), and Chalcocite (Cu<font size="10">2</font>S).By far the largest amounts of copper are found in the crust in bodies known as porphyry copper deposits. Australia's main copper mining centres are in the Mount Isa/Cloncurry region of Queensland and at Olympic Dam in South Australia.]]></geology></element><element><name>Zinc Zn</name><use><![CDATA[Zinc is the most used non-ferrous metal after aluminium and copper.Almost half of the zinc produced is used for galvanising steel to protect it from rust. Galvanised steel is used in many industrial applications including structural steel, cars, roofing, fencing, wire ropes and cables, tanks, reinforcing bars and fasteners.Zinc is used to make brass (with copper), and is used in die casting alloys.Zinc compounds and dusts are used in fertilisers, batteries, paint and rubber tyres.Zinc is essential to the human body.Zinc is used in vitamin pills, cosmetics and sun screens.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[The main zinc mineral is sphalerite (zinc sulphide, ZnS). This contains 67 per cent zinc.Sulphides containing zinc form mainly in a type of submarine hydrothermal deposit called volcanogenic (creating a volcano) massive sulfide deposit, in which seawater on the ocean floor flows through fractures in the oceanic crust. The waters are heated by the nearby magma, producing seawater convection which reacts with neighbouring rocks to dissolve metals. These metals are transported to the ocean floor where they mix with cold bottom waters. The sudden decrease in temperature causes the metals to precipitate and become incorporated into sediments of the ocean floor.Zinc also forms in hydrothermal veins, together with lead and silver.Australia ranks first in the world in economic zinc resources. China and Canada are also significant producers of zinc.]]></geology></element><element><name>Gallium Ga</name><use><![CDATA[The biggest use of gallium, as gallium arsenide (GaAs), is to make lasers because it can change electricity directly into laser light. Lasers are used in many different types of appliances, including CD and DVD players.Gallium arsenide is also used in light-emitting diodes (LEDs), solar cells, semi-conductors, transistors, and some integrated circuits.Enormous amounts of gallium have been used in the search for a particle known as a solar neutrino. Two such experiments used a total of 90 tonnes of gallium.Because of its high boiling point, gallium is used to make thermometers that measure very high temperatures.Gallium is also used to make mirrors.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Gallium does not easily combine with other elements or ions to form ore minerals. However, it is found in very small amounts in a number of minerals and ores, the most important of which is bauxite (aluminium ore). In fact, gallium is a by-product of aluminium production.]]></geology></element><element><name>Germanium Ge</name><use><![CDATA[Germanium is a metalloid (an element that has both metallic and non-metallic properties), making it a semiconductor. This means that it conducts some electricity like a metal, but not all of the electricity that a true conductor like copper would conduct. Therefore, germanium is important in the electronics industry where it is used to make transistors and semiconductors.The fibre optic industry accounts for a large amount of the germanium used each year.It is also used as a catalyst to produce polymers.Because infrared radiation can pass through germanium, it is used in infrared equipment.It is also used to treat some types of cancers.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Germanium was first discovered and isolated from the mineral argyrodite. However, there are no significant argyrodite deposits.Germanium is produced as a by-product of zinc and copper-zinc-lead ores where it is found as a trace (very small amount) element.Germanium also occurs in significant amounts in coal, although not all coal contains germanium.]]></geology></element><element><name>Arsenic As</name><use><![CDATA[As a metalloid (an element that has both metallic and non-metallic properties), arsenic is a semiconductor. This means that it conducts some electricity like a metal, but not all of the electricity that a true conductor like copper would conduct. This useful property means that arsenic is used to make gallium arsenide semiconductors for use in electronic devices.Arsenic is used in glass-making.In the past, arsenic compounds were used as agricultural insecticides, but because they are so toxic this use has largely stopped.Interestingly, a very small amount of arsenic is necessary for good health and growth of animals, including humans.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Arsenic very rarely occurs in its pure form in nature.The most common arsenic mineral is arsenopyrite, a compound of iron, arsenic, and sulphur. Many less-common minerals contain arsenic, including orpiment and realgar, which are arsenic sulphides.Most arsenic is obtained not from an ore, but as a by-product in the treatment of gold, silver, copper, and other metal ores. In fact, environmental laws require that arsenic is removed from these ores so that it does not enter the environment.]]></geology></element><element><name>Selenium Se</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Bromine Br</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Krypton Kr</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Rubidium Rb</name><use><![CDATA[Used as a catalyst, photocells, and vacuum and cathode-ray tubes. While rubidium is used in some medical and electronic applications, mostly it is used in laboratory studies.Rubidium may some day be used in space travel in ion engines that will power spacecraft. It could also be used to create very thin batteries.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Rubidium does not combine with other elements or ions to create minerals. It is found, though, in trace amounts in minerals that contain other alkali metals. These include caesium-rich and potassium-rich zeolites, pollucite and leucite, and the lithium-rich mica called zinnwaldite (a variety of the mineral lepidolite).Most rubidium is retrieved from lepidolite and pollucite in pegmatites. A pegmatite is an igneous rock where the magma cools so slowly that very large crystals form. Unusual and rare elements are typical of the minerals found in pegmatites.]]></geology></element><element><name>Strontium Sr</name><use><![CDATA[About three-quarters of the strontium consumed each year is used in the glass picture tubes of colour television sets, to prevent x-rays escaping from the tubes.Some strontium is used to make special magnets called ferrite ceramic magnets.Strontium gives road flares and fireworks a bright red colour.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Strontium is recovered from two strontium minerals: strontianite (strontium carbonate) and celestite (strontium sulphate).Celestite, the more common of these two, is formed by the precipitation of salts from natural brines during evaporation of lagoons, and saline lakes. Gypsum, salt and dolomite are also formed by this process.]]></geology></element><element><name>Yttrium Y</name><use><![CDATA[Yttrium, in combination with vanadium and europium, is a phosphor that gives the red colour in colour television tubes. This is a major use of yttrium. It is also used in laser systems.Yttrium is alloyed with other metals such as chromium, aluminium, and magnesium as it adds strength.Yttrium oxide is used to produce yttrium-iron-garnets, which are very effective microwave filters. Because yttrium oxide has a high melting point, it helps to make glass more shock resistant, and less likely to expand when heated.Yttrium-iron garnet is very efficient as a transmitter of sound energy. It also is very good at converting sound energy into other forms of energy.Yttrium-aluminium garnet is a gemstone that has the appearance (and almost the hardness) of a diamond.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Yttrium is never found in nature in the free element form.Yttrium is mainly found in the ores monazite (Ce,La,Nd,Th)PO<font size="10">4</font>, a rare earth phosphate mineral common in heavy mineral sands, and bastnaesite (Ce,La)(CO<font size="10">3</font>)F Both ores contain small amounts of all of the rare earth metals. Another mineral, xenotime (YPO<font size="10">4</font>), also contains yttrium.Weathering of rocks containing these minerals concentrates monazite and xenotime in heavy mineral placer deposits because of their resistance to chemical attack and high specific gravity.Rock samples from the moon have a relatively high yttrium content.]]></geology></element><element><name>Zirconium Zr</name><use><![CDATA[Zirconium is used in pumps and valves, and in the cores of nuclear reactors because it is so resistant to corrosion.Zirconium oxide is used to make laboratory crucibles and to line furnaces. Other Zirconium compounds are used in deodorants, flashbulbs, and lamp filaments.Zirconium alloyed with niobium becomes superconductive. This means it is able to conduct electricity with very little loss of energy as a result of electrical resistance. Superconductivity is possible only at very low temperatures.Because zirconium does not absorb neutrons, it is useful as a coating on nuclear fuel parts in nuclear reactors.Zirconia, an oxide of zirconium (ZrO<font size="10">2</font>), is used as a gemstone. Cubic zirconia, which is hard and clear, is marketed as an inexpensive diamond-like gemstone. Coloured cubic zirconia is sold as imitation jewellery because it looks like many more expensive gemstones.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Zirconium is found in two minerals: zircon (zirconium silicate, ZrSiO<font size="10">4</font>) and baddeleyite (zirconium oxide, ZrO<font size="10">2</font>).Zircon is found in very small amounts in some igneous rocks. Weathering of these rocks concentrates the minerals such as zircon, rutile and ilmenite to form deposits in stream beds, where flowing water has washed away the lighter materials. These are called placer deposits. Once they are in these deposits they are called heavy minerals because of their high density and high specific gravity.]]></geology></element><element><name>Niobium Nb</name><use><![CDATA[Niobium is used in the manufacture of some stainless steels. When it is alloyed with nonferrous metals, niobium produces metals with good strength and other properties useful in pipeline construction and arc-welding.Niobium is used in advanced engineering systems such as those used in the Gemini space program. Some magnets contain niobium.Because of its bluish colour, niobium is used for 'body art' products, such as navel rings.The ability of niobium to capture neutrons makes it useful in the nuclear industry.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Columbite, the most widespread niobium mineral, is an important ore for this metal.Columbite is a natural oxide of niobium, tantalum, ferrous iron, and manganese. It forms in granite pegmatites. A pegmatite is an igneous deposit where the magma cools so slowly that very large crystals form. Unusual and rare elements are typical of the minerals found in pegmatites.]]></geology></element><element><name>Molybdenum Mo</name><use><![CDATA[The two largest uses of molybdenum are as an alloy in stainless steels, and to make steel stronger at high temperatures.Superalloys (those developed for use at high temperatures) of steel and molybdenum are used in gas turbine parts, and chemical processing equipment.Molybdenum is important in the chemical and lubricant industries. It is used in paint pigments. It is used as a catalyst, corrosion inhibitor, and smoke and flame retardant.Molybdenum disulphide is used as a dry lubricant on space vehicles, where it also is resistant to high loads and temperatures.Because of its high melting point (2610�C), molybdenum is used in filament supports in light bulbs, in metal-working dies, and in furnace parts.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Molybdenum is not found in the free metal form in nature.Its main ore is molybdenite (molybdenum sulphide, MoS<font size="10">2</font>). Molybdenum is also recovered as a by-product of copper and tungsten production.Molybdenum skarns are the main sources of molybdenum. They form when a special type of granite rock come into contact with sedimentary rocks. The hot fluids carried by the igneous rock change the surrounding rock, and new minerals form from the interaction of hot fluids and the cold rock. This process is called contact metamorphism, and the metamorphosed rock, including the new minerals formed, is called a skarn.]]></geology></element><element><name>Technetium Tc</name><use><![CDATA[Technetium was the first element to be produced artificially.Technetium-99, a synthetic isotope, emits gamma rays that can be detected by monitoring devices. Because this isotope is relatively safe, it can be used as a radioactive tracer in the body to study structures and physiological actions.This metal is an excellent superconductor at extremely low temperatures.Technetium is a remarkable inhibitor of corrosion in steel.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Technetium is produced artificially.Since its discovery, searches for the element on earth have been made without success. If it does exist, the concentration must be very small.Technetium has been found in matter from space.]]></geology></element><element><name>Ruthenium Ru</name><use><![CDATA[Ruthenium is one of the most effective hardeners for platinum and palladium. It is alloyed with these metals to make electrical contacts that need to resist severe wear.The corrosion resistance of titanium is improved one-hundred times by addition of only 0.1% ruthenium.Ruthenium compounds can be versatile catalysts. Hydrogen sulphide can be split catalytically by light using an aqueous suspension of cadmium sulphide particles loaded with ruthenium dioxide. This process can be used to remove hydrogen sulphide from oil.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Ruthenium belongs to the platinum group elements.As sulphide compounds form in magma, they sink into the floor of the magma chamber and trap the platinum group elements out of the liquid magma. After uplift and erosion of these magmatic rocks, the sulphides, which have high concentrations of nickel, chromium, and the platinum group elements, are found as thin layers that can be traced for long distances.]]></geology></element><element><name>Rhodium Rh</name><use><![CDATA[Rhodium is used to harden platinum and palladium in alloys that are used for furnace windings, thermocouple elements, bushings for glass fibre production, electrodes for aircraft spark plugs, and laboratory crucibles.It is used as an electrical contact as it has a low electrical resistance, and is highly resistant to corrosion.Plated rhodium produced by electroplating or evaporation is very hard, and is used for optical instruments and jewellery.Rhodium is a catalyst in car catalytic converters, where it helps to clean up exhaust gases.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Rhodium belongs to the platinum group elements.As sulphide compounds form in magma, they sink into the floor of the magma chamber and trap the platinum group elements out of the liquid magma. After uplift and erosion of these magmatic rocks, the sulphides, which have high concentrations of nickel, chromium, and the platinum group elements, are found as thin layers that can be traced for long distances.]]></geology></element><element><name>Palladium Pd</name><use><![CDATA[Palladium, together with platinum and rhodium, are the main components in catalysts that reduce vehicle exhaust emissions.The second largest demand for palladium is in electronics, where it is used to make capacitors needed in cellular telephones, personal and notebook computers, fax machines, and in car and home electronics.Palladium is widely used in dental alloys because it makes them easy to work with, strong, and resistant to discolouration.Palladium is used in jewellery, either on its own or in 'white gold' (a combination of palladium and gold). In this alloy the yellow colour of the gold fades and the alloy becomes whiter.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Palladium belongs to the platinum group which includes platinum, palladium, rhodium, iridium, osmium, and ruthenium. These elements commonly occur together in nature and are among the scarcest of the metallic elements.Palladium and the rest of the elements of this group are found in thin layers of metal ores called massive sulphides. These sulphide ores are found in dark igneous rocks with high iron and magnesium content.Palladium is found as the free metal associated with platinum and other platinum group metals in Australia, Brazil, Russia, Ethiopia, and North and South America.]]></geology></element><element><name>Silver Ag</name><use><![CDATA[Like gold, silver has been extensively used for jewellery, medals and ornaments. The main uses of silver include electronics, silver-zinc and silver-cadmium batteries, brazing alloys, mirrors, medicinal compounds, dental fillings and as catalysts.Silver compounds, sensitive to light, are used in photography.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Silver is sometimes found in the free element form, but more often in compounds with sulfur such as argentite or tetrahedrite. The main silver mineral is tetrahedrite.Warm to hot (hydrothermal) fluids generated within the earth form copper, lead and zinc deposits, which contain silver. These fluids may be trapped below the surface in cracks where galena, with trace silver, and other minerals precipitate to make vein deposits. Where limestones occur the fluids fill cavities to form rich but patchy lead-zinc-silver deposits. Some fluids can reach the ocean floor, in areas of underwater volcanic activity, to form deposits.Partially eroded deposits exposed at the surface were relatively easily discovered. Examples are the Broken Hill deposit in New South Wales and the Mt Isa deposit in Queensland.Silver which has been used for photography is usually recovered and recycled]]></geology></element><element><name>Cadmium Cd</name><use><![CDATA[The single most important use of cadmium is in the production of nickel-cadmium (Ni-Cad) rechargeable batteries. This accounts for about three-quarters of the cadmium consumed annually. Nickel-cadmium batteries are used in cellular phones, hand-held cordless power tools, cameras, portable computers, and many household products.Cadmium is useful in a small number of other applications. Cadmium sulphide (greenockite, also called cadmium yellow) is used as a paint pigment.Cadmium compounds are used both in black and white and colour television tubes.Because cadmium absorbs neutrons, it is used in nuclear reactor control rods to keep the fission reactions under control.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Cadmium ores are rare.Cadmium occurs in very small quantities in zinc ores such as sphalerite (zinc sulphide, ZnS).Greenockite, (cadmium sulphide, CdS), is the only known mineral containing cadmium as an essential constituent.Both sphalerite and greenockite form in hydrothermal veins, which are cavities or fractures in rocks where hot fluids coming from deeper parts of the earth's crust precipitate out their metal-rich minerals.]]></geology></element><element><name>Indium In</name><use><![CDATA[Indium, in the form of indium-tin oxide, is used in the thin film coatings which are used to make liquid crystal displays (LCDs). This is the largest use of indium, accounting for one-half of its use each year.Indium phosphide is used to make photovoltaic devices (devices that transform light energy into electricity), semi-conductors, high-speed transistors, specialised solders, and metal alloys.Indium alloys have been used in control rods within nuclear reactors.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Indium is found in significant amounts in ores of lead, copper, and tin. The highest concentrations of indium are in tin ores.Indium can also be obtained as a by-product from some zinc ores, particularly from the mineral sphalerite.]]></geology></element><element><name>Tin Sn</name><use><![CDATA[As tin does not corrode and is non-toxic it is used to coat steel to produce cans in which food can be stored. Tin and alloys of tin are used to make solder for the electronics industry. Alloys of tin are used in metallic coatings.Inorganic compounds of tin are used in ceramics and glazes.Organic compounds of tin are used in plastics, wood preservatives, pesticides and fire retardants.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Cassiterite (SnO<font size="10">2</font>) is by far the most important tin ore. Tin is also recovered from sulphide minerals such as stannite (Cu<font size="10">2</font>FeSnS<font size="10">4</font>).Tin occurs in both primary and secondary deposits. Primary tin deposits, accounting for about 20% of the tin deposits, occur as hard-rock veins or lodes. Secondary tin deposits occur as placer deposits. Placer deposits are deposits of heavy minerals in streams, valleys, the sea floor or beaches.Tin and tungsten often occur together.Most of the world's tin supply comes from China, Malaysia, Indonesia, and Thailand.]]></geology></element><element><name>Antimony Sb</name><use><![CDATA[The most important use of antimony is to produce chemicals that are added to plastics, textiles, rubber, and other materials to make them fire-proof.Antimony alloyed with other metals usually makes them harder. This is important in lead-acid batteries (the sort found in cars) where antimony makes the lead harder and stronger.Some antimony alloys, such as Babbitt metal (an alloy of antimony, tin, copper, and sometimes lead), are useful as machine bearings because they are soft and slippery.Pewter, an alloy of antimony and tin, is used to make such things as plates, pitchers and cups.A declining use of antimony is to make type metal for printing newspapers and magazines. Antimony is one of very few substances (bismuth and water are two others) which expands when it cools and freezes. Therefore, type metal containing antimony fills every corner of the moulds used to prepare sharp type for printing. Electronic printing has reduced this need for antimony.Antimony oxide is a brilliant yellow colour, accounting for its use as a pigment.A tiny amount of highly purified antimony metal is used in the computer industry to make semiconductors. This antimony has to be 99.999% pure!]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Antimony rarely occurs in its pure metallic form in nature.It readily combines with other elements, usually including sulphur, to form over 100 different minerals. Of these, only stibnite (SbS<font size="10">3</font>) is mined commercially as a source for antimony.Antimony is found in trace (that is, very small) amounts in silver, copper and lead ores. Some antimony can be obtained from these ores when they are smelted.]]></geology></element><element><name>Tellurium Te</name><use><![CDATA[Half of the tellurium consumed each year is used to in the manufacture of iron and steel products.Tellurium alloyed with copper makes the copper more ductile (easier to stretch into wires). When alloyed with lead it prevents corrosion.Tellurium is used to make catalysts and chemicals. Some of these chemicals are used in the petroleum industry and in making rubber.Tellurium is used to make solar panels, where it increases the efficiency of power generation.Tellurium is used to produce blasting caps for explosives.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Tellurium can be recovered from materials left during the refining of copper.Although there are large quantities of tellurium in some gold and lead deposits, these deposits are not processed for their tellurium content.Tellurium is present in coal, and in some lower-grade copper deposits. However, the cost of recovering tellurium from these deposits is too high to make it worth the effort.]]></geology></element><element><name>Iodine I</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Xenon Xe</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Caesium Cs</name><use><![CDATA[The most accurate clock in the world, the atomic clock, measures time based on the very precise vibration of the electrons in the outer shell of the caesium atom. This clock is accurate to within 5 seconds every 300 years!Metallic caesium is used in photoelectric cells and infrared detectors. Caesium and its compounds are used as catalysts in chemical reactions, while Caesium compounds are used in special alkaline batteries designed to work in subzero climates.Caesium carbonate is used in the production of some glass and glass products. The radioactive isotope, caesium-137, is used in radiation therapy to treat cancers.Space travel engineers have discovered that burning caesium in space is a very efficient form of fuel. It is about 140 times more efficient than any other fuel.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Many minerals contain significant amounts of caesium, including mica, beryl, feldspar, petalite, and pollucite.Most caesium is retrieved from the mineral pollucite, which is found in lithium-rich granitic pegmatites.]]></geology></element><element><name>Barium Ba</name><use><![CDATA[Barium is used as a heavy additive in oil-well drilling. It is used also in the paper and rubber industries, and as a filler in cloth, ink, and plastics products.Barium carbonate is used as a rat poison.Barium sulfate is used in radiography to image internal organs. Patients are required to take a barium meal. It is also used as a pigment for paint and in glassmaking.Barium is alloyed with other metals to make spark plugs.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Most barium is obtained from the mineral, barite.Barite is usually mined from layers of sedimentary rock which formed when barite precipitated onto the bottom of the ocean. Some smaller mines obtain barite from veins which formed when barium sulphate precipitated from hot underground waters.Some barite is a by-product of mining lead, zinc, silver, and other metal ores.]]></geology></element><element><name>Lanthanum La</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Cerium Ce</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Praseodymium Pr</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Neodynium Nd</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Promethium Pm</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Samarium Sm</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Europium Eu</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Gadolinium Gd</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Terbium Tb</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Dysprosium Dy</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Holmium Ho</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Erbium Er</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Thulium Tm</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Ytterbium Yb</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Lutetium Lu</name><use><![CDATA[Stable forms of lutetium are used as catalysts in the distillation of petroleum and for other chemical reactions.Some alloys are made with lutetium.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Lutetium is never found in nature in the free element form.Lutetium is mainly found in the ores monazite (Ce,La,Nd,Th)PO<font size="10">4</font>,, a rare earth phosphate mineral common in heavy mineral sands, and bastnaesite (Ce,La)(CO<font size="10">3</font>)F. Both ores contain small amounts of all of the rare earth metals.]]></geology></element><element><name>Hafnium Hf</name><use><![CDATA[The most significant use of hafnium is in the production of special alloys known as superalloys. These are mixtures of metals that are designed to withstand high-stress situations, such as very high temperatures and pressures. Metals used in these alloys include iron, nickel, chromium, titanium, niobium, and hafnium.Because of its ability to absorb neutrons, hafnium is used to control fission reactions in nuclear reactors, including those that power nuclear submarines.Hafnium is also used as a scavenger metal in the retrieval of oxygen and nitrogen. A scavenger metal is one which aids in the collection of gases without reacting with them to form other compounds.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Hafnium is never found in the free element form in nature.The mineral zircon is the primary ore source of hafnium. Most zircon, and therefore, hafnium, is mined from titanium-rich, heavy-mineral sand deposits.Hafnium is also found in the minerals alvite [(Hf,Th, Zr)SiO<font size="10">4</font>.xH<font size="10">2</font>O] and thortveitite.As zirconium minerals (zircon, baddelyite) contain 1-3% hafnium, most hafnium is obtained as a by-product of zirconium production.]]></geology></element><element><name>Tantalum Ta</name><use><![CDATA[The electronics industry is the largest consumer of tantalum; it is used to manufacture capacitors, devices that regulate the flow of electricity. Tantalum capacitors are found in mobile phones, laptop computers and video cameras.Tantalum is used to make steel alloys with desirable properties such as high melting point, high strength, and good ductility (ability to be made into wire or thin sheets). These alloys are used to make turbine blades for power stations and jet engines, and for aircraft and missile manufacture.Because tantalum is very unreactive it is useful in the chemical and nuclear industries to line reactors.Tantalum is used in surgical procedures as it is tolerated well inside the body. For example, it can be used in sutures, and as repair plates for the cranium.The oxide of tantalum is used to make special glass with a high refractive index for camera lenses.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Tantalum is found in pegmatites mainly in the minerals tantalite [(Fe,Mn)Ta<font size="10">2</font>O<font size="10">6</font>] and microlite and wodginite. A pegmatite is an igneous deposit where the magma (molten rock) cools so slowly that very large crystals form. Unusual and rare elements are typical of the minerals found in pegmatites.The largest source of tantalum is from the Greenbushes and Wodgina mines in Western Australia. These mines produce between 25 and 35% of the world's supply of tantalum.Tantalum ores are also found in Brazil, Mozambique, Thailand, Portugal, Nigeria, Zaire and Canada.]]></geology></element><element><name>Tungsten W</name><use><![CDATA[Tungsten and its alloys are used to make light bulb filaments, television tubes, electrical contact points for car distributors, X-ray targets, electrical windings, and heating elements for electrical furnaces.Tungsten carbide is important to the metal-working, mining, and petroleum industries.Calcium and magnesium tungstates are used in fluorescent lighting.Tungsten salts are used in the chemical and tanning industries.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Tungsten is found in wolframite (iron-manganese tungstate, FeWO<font size="10">4</font> / MnWO<font size="10">4</font>) and scheelite (calcium tungstate, CaWO<font size="10">4</font>).Tungsten and tin commonly occur together and are associated with ore deposits related to high silica granite intrusion into the upper crust. Scheelite can form in skarn deposits (where limestones or marble are heated by intrusion of an igneous rock) and in quartz veins with gold in metamorphic rocks.China, Canada and Russia have large reserves of tungsten. Recycled tungsten accounts for a significant proportion of the total use of this metal.]]></geology></element><element><name>Rhenium Re</name><use><![CDATA[Because of its very high melting point, rhenium is used to make high temperature alloys that are used in jet engine parts. It is also used to make strong alloys with nickel.Rhenium alloys are used to make temperature controls, heating elements, electrical contacts, electromagnets, and semiconductors.An alloy of rhenium and molybdenum is a superconductor of electricity at very low temperatures. These superalloys account for the majority of the rhenium used each year.Rhenium is also used as a catalyst in the petroleum industry to make lead-free petrol.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Rhenium is never found in the free metal form in nature.Rhenium is found as a minor component in the mineral gadolinite, which contains beryllium, and molybdenite. It is extracted as a byproduct from processing plants extracting molybdenum from molybdenite.]]></geology></element><element><name>Osmium Os</name><use><![CDATA[Most osmium is used to produce very hard alloys with other metals of the platinum group. These alloys are found in fountain pen tips, instrument pivots, and electrical contacts.An alloy of platinum and osmium (in the ratio of 90:10) is used in implants such as pacemakers and replacement heart valves.Osmium tetroxide (OsO<font size="10">4</font>) is used to detect fingerprints, and to stain fatty tissue for microscope slides.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Osmium is found as the free element in iridiosmium, a naturally occurring alloy of iridium and osmium. It is also found in platinum-bearing sands and ores of the Urals, North America, and South America.]]></geology></element><element><name>Iridium Ir</name><use><![CDATA[Iridium is used to make crucibles and other equipment used at high temperatures. It is also used in electrical contacts and as a hardening agent for platinum.An alloy of iridium and osmium is used to make pen tips and compass bearings.Some sparkplugs contain an alloy of platinum and iridium.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Iridium is found as the free element alloyed with platinum and other platinum metals.Naturally occurring alloys include osmiridium and iridiosmium, both mixtures of iridium and osmium.]]></geology></element><element><name>Platinum Pt</name><use><![CDATA[Platinum is used mainly as a catalyst for the control of car and industrial plant emissions and in the production of acids, organic chemicals, and pharmaceuticals.Platinum alloyed with gold, silver and copper is used in dentistry, for example in the creation of braces to straighten teeth.Platinum is used to treat cancers, particularly leukaemias.An alloy of platinum and osmium is used in heart pacemakers and replacement heart valves.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Platinum and the other elements of the platinum group always occur together in dark igneous rocks derived directly from magma found between the core and the earth's crust.The process in which these elements concentrate in magmas is called magmatic segregation. As sulphide compounds form they sink into the floor of the magma chamber, and trap the platinum group elements out of the liquid magma.]]></geology></element><element><name>Gold Au</name><use><![CDATA[Gold is used as a store of wealth for many countries and individuals. The main uses of gold are jewellery, dentistry and for decoration and art work. As it conducts electricity and is ductile, gold is used for wiring in computers - from digital radios to microwaves, from telephone systems to rocket launchers! Gold is very useful for wiring that is difficult to repair, such as under water and in outer space, because it does not corrode or wear out quickly. Gold coated connector pads and gold wires are at the heart of computerized wheelchairs. Gold is inert so it can be used safely in the human body as a wire to join broken bones or to cover a implant to go into the heart. New uses are being found for gold as a catalyst, as a genetic marker and in the field of electronics.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Gold usually occurs in its metallic state but it may also be found in compounds with sulfur. There are two main types of gold deposits. Gold found in cracks or veins in rocks are called lode or vein deposits. Alluvial deposits are formed where gold has been eroded out of vein deposits and deposited in the sediment of rivers and lakes. About two-thirds of Australia's gold resources occur in Western Australia.]]></geology></element><element><name>Mercury Hg</name><use><![CDATA[Mercury is used in thermometers and some scientific equipment, although the use of mercury in thermometers used in schools has ceased due to its toxicity.Mercury is used in the manufacture of chlorine and caustic soda (NaOH).Mercury is useful in electronics and electrical applications and in fluorescent light tubes.Although mercury was used in batteries, newer types of batteries use other, less hazardous metals.Combined with other metals, mercury is used for dental fillings called amalgams.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Mercury only occurs rarely as the free liquid form in nature. Overall, it is a rare element in the earth's crust.Its main source is the mineral cinnabar  (HgS). This was mined by the Romans for its mercury, and still is mined for its mercury today.]]></geology></element><element><name>Thallium Tl</name><use><![CDATA[Thallium is used in devices that detect gamma radiation and infrared radiation.Thallium added to glass increases its density and refractive index (that is, its ability to break light into its component colours).It is used as a catalyst to create certain organic compounds.Radioactive thallium compounds are used in medical applications.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Thallium is found in a small number of rare minerals, including crooksite and lorandite. These minerals form with the zinc sulfide, sphalerite. As a result, thallium is recovered as a by-product of processing zinc ores.Thallium is also recovered from lead and copper ores, and from the dust that accumulates in the flues of copper, zinc and lead smelters.There are other sources of thallium. The world's coal reserves contain about 630 million kilograms of thallium. And thallium is found in manganese nodules that form on the ocean floor.]]></geology></element><element><name>Lead Pb</name><use><![CDATA[About 60% of all lead used is found in lead-acid batteries. These batteries provide the starting power for all types of vehicles, and are a standby power source where a constant power supply is vital, such as in hospitals, submarines, computer installations and telephone exchanges.Lead is used as a shield against radiation in the nuclear industry, and in hospital X-ray departments. It is added to the glass of television and computer screens to prevent potentially harmful radiation from escaping.Other uses of lead include plumbing, solder, sound-proofing, crystal glass, type metal, ammunition, as a protective cover for undersea cables, as a UV protector to some plastics used outdoors, and in the chemical industry.Recently, environmental and health concerns about lead have reduced its use in paint pigments and petrol.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[The main lead mineral is galena (PbS) which contains 86.6% lead. Other lead minerals are cerussite (PbCO<font size="10">3</font>) and anglesite (PbSO<font size="10">4</font>).Deposits containing lead form from hot (hydrothermal) fluids generated within the earth. These fluids may be trapped below the surface in cracks where galena and other minerals precipitate to form vein deposits. Significant amounts of lead are recovered as a by-product from zinc mines, and silver-copper deposits.More than one million tons of lead are recovered through recycling each year, most of it from batteries.]]></geology></element><element><name>Bismuth Bi</name><use><![CDATA[Bismuth is used as a carrier of uranium in nuclear reactors. It is also used in ceramics and paints, and is a catalyst in some industrial reactions.Bismuth is often alloyed with other metals: - Added to iron, bismuth makes this metal easier to work. - With tin and cadmium, it forms alloys that have a low melting point, and which are used for safety devices in fire detectors and fire extinguishers.Bismuth and many of its alloys expand slightly when they solidify (freeze). This allows these metals to fill all corners of a mould to form a perfect replica of the item being produced. This is also a valued property when used in soldering plumbing (joining pipes).Bismuth oxychloride is used extensively in cosmetics.Bismuth subnitrate and subcarbonate are used in medicine.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[The most common bismuth minerals are bismuthinite and bismite. Generally, these and other bismuth minerals occur in minute quantities within ores of other metals, such as those of gold, silver, lead, zinc, and tungsten.Bismuth is usually an indicator of high-temperature mineral deposits, forming in veins with quartz and some metallic minerals. These deposits are also found where granite intrusions are in contact with other rocks such as limestone.]]></geology></element><element><name>Polonium Po</name><use><![CDATA[Polonium is used on brushes for removing dust from photographic films and as a source of neutrons in various applications.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Polonium is produced through decay of the small quantities of the bismuth isotope 210Bi present in pitchblende (uranite, largely UO<font size="10">2</font>). Uranium ores might contain about 0.0001 g of polonium in a tonne of ore.]]></geology></element><element><name>Astatine At</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Radon Rn</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Francium Fr</name><use><![CDATA[Francium has no uses.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Francium is found in uranium ores where it occurs as a rare isotope (223Fr) with a very short half life (22 minutes). Because of this there is only 20-30g of this element in the earth’s crust at any one time.]]></geology></element><element><name>Radium Ra</name><use><![CDATA[Its most common use is in the production of self-luminous paints. It was used expensively in the medical area as a treatment for conditions like cancer.]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Radium is found naturally in uranium ores such as pitchblende (mostly UO<font size="10">2</font>). It is fairly abundant in the earths crust with some estimates suggesting that every square kilometre of soil to a depth of a 40 cm contains about 1 g of radium.]]></geology></element><element><name>Actinium Ac</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[Actinium is found naturally in uranium ores such as pitchblende (mostly UO<font size="10">2</font>). A tonne of pitchblende might yield just about 0.1 g of actinium.]]></geology></element><element><name>Thorium Th</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Protactinium Pa</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Uranium U</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Neptunium Np</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Plutonium Pu</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Americium Am</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Curium Cm</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Berkelium Bk</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Californium Cf</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Einsteinium Es</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Fermium Fm</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Mendelevium Md</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Nobelium No</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Lawrencium Lr</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Rutherfordium Rf</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Dubnium Db</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Seaborgium Sg</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Bohrium Bh</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Hassium Hs</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Meitnerium Mt</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Darmstadtium Ds</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Unununium Uuu</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Ununbium Uub</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Ununtrium Uut</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Ununquadium Uuq</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Ununpentium Uup</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Ununhexium Uuh</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Ununseptium Uus</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element><element><name>Ununoctium Uuo</name><use><![CDATA[]]></use><geology><![CDATA[]]></geology></element></elementlist>