<exterior>	<objects>		<Obj>Car</Obj>		<Descr>The major metals in car are aluminium, iron, lead, nickel, platinum and zinc. Aluminium is obtained from bauxite; iron is extracted from minerals such as hematite, and limonite; lead comes from galena; and nickel occurs in pentlandite. Chromium is extracted from Chromite. Platinum is extracted from Pentlandite. Zinc is obtained from minerals such sphalerite. The steel used to make the body of the car contains iron mixed with a number of other elements such as carbon, copper, manganese, phosphorus and silicon. The exhaust system in the car contains palladium. Other body components in the car are made from aluminium. Gold is used for the electronic circuits of the airbag mechanism.</Descr>		<Symbol>Al, Cr, Cu, Fe, Pb, Mg, Mn, Ni, Pd, Rh, Si, Zn, Pt, Au</Symbol>		<Names>aluminium, chromium, copper, iron, lead, magnesium, manganese, nickel, palladium, rhodium, silicon, zinc, platinum, gold</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Bike</Obj>		<Descr>Many bikes are made from aluminium but modern competition bikes are  made from C, Ni, Ti, and possibly Cr and Mg</Descr>		<Symbol>Al, Ti, Fe, Ni</Symbol>		<Names>aluminium, titanium, iron, nickel, </Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Paint tin</Obj>		<Descr>The paint tin is made of steel and the paint contains titanium pigments and possibly compounds of iron, copper, cobalt, manganese to provide the colour.</Descr>		<Symbol>Fe, Ti, Cu, Mn, Co</Symbol>		<Names>iron, titanium, copper, manganese, cobalt</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Fertiliser</Obj>		<Descr>Fertiliser contains a range of metallic elements and many non-metals like nitrogen, phosphorus and carbon.</Descr>		<Symbol>Cu, Fe, Mn, K</Symbol>		<Names>copper, iron, manganese, potassium</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Number</Obj>		<Descr>The brass house numbers contain both copper and zinc. Copper comes from minerals such as chalcopyrite, and zinc from minerals such as sphalerite.</Descr>		<Symbol>Cu, Zn</Symbol>		<Names>copper, zinc</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Concrete</Obj>		<Descr>The concrete path is made of concrete, which comes from rocks such as limestone, gypsum and shale. Clay rich in iron is used to make bricks.</Descr>		<Symbol>Fe</Symbol>		<Names>iron</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Window</Obj>		<Descr>The aluminium in the window frame comes from bauxite. The glass contains silicon derived from quartz.</Descr>		<Symbol>Al, Si</Symbol>		<Names>aluminium, silicon</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Roof</Obj>		<Descr>The ceramic roof tiles contain beryllium, obtained from the mineral beryl. Tellurium sometimes is used to make ceramics.</Descr>		<Symbol>Be, Te</Symbol>		<Names>beryllium, tellurium</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Eaves</Obj>		<Descr>The timber in the eaves, walls, roof and floor are fastened together with nails and screws made of iron extracted from iron oxides such as hematite and limonite, and zinc from minerals such as sphalerite.</Descr>		<Symbol>Fe, Zn</Symbol>		<Names>iron, zinc</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Paint</Obj>		<Descr>Paints contain titanium from the mineral rutile, cobalt from cobaltite, and manganese from minerals such as pyrolusite. Radium, from radium ores such as pitchblende, can be used to make luminous paints.</Descr>		<Symbol>Co, Mn, Ra, Ti</Symbol>		<Names>cobalt, manganese, radium, titanium</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Steel rails</Obj>		<Descr>The rails are made of steel that contains iron, carbon, copper, manganese, phosphorus and silicon.</Descr>		<Symbol>Fe, Cu, Mn, Si</Symbol>		<Names>iron, copper , manganese, silicon</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Gutters</Obj>		<Descr>Galvanised steel used to make gutters contains three main elements: aluminium, iron and zinc. Aluminium is obtained from bauxite, iron from iron oxides such as hematite and limonite, and zinc from minerals such as sphalerite.</Descr>		<Symbol>Al, Fe</Symbol>		<Names>aluminium, iron</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Tools</Obj>		<Descr>Tools contain iron, which comes from hematite or limonite, and nickel extracted from pentlandite.</Descr>		<Symbol>Fe, Ni</Symbol>		<Names>iron, nickel</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Scooter</Obj>		<Descr>The scooter is mainly made from aluminium.</Descr>		<Symbol>Al</Symbol>		<Names>aluminium</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Ladder</Obj>		<Descr>The ladder is made from aluminium.</Descr>		<Symbol>Al</Symbol>		<Names>aluminium</Names>	</objects></exterior>