<kitchen>	<objects>		<Obj>Tiles</Obj>		<Descr>The ceramic floor tiles contain beryllium, obtained from the mineral beryl. Tellurium sometimes is used to make ceramics.</Descr>		<Symbol>Be, Te</Symbol>		<Names>beryllium, tellurium</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Radio</Obj>		<Descr>Clock radios are like computers, in that they have circuit boards that contain gold, silica, zinc, aluminium, nickel, iron and about thirty other minerals. The nickel comes from pentlandite, aluminium from bauxite, iron from minerals such as hematite and limonite, and zinc from minerals such as sphalerite. The electrical wiring is made of copper obtained from minerals such as chalcopyrite. Gallium and germanium are part of transistors. Some of the other elements found in very small amounts in the electronic components in radios are niobium, palladium, platinum, rhodium, ruthenium, selenium, tantalum terbium, titanium, vanadium and yttrium.</Descr>		<Symbol>Al, Au, Ba, Cu, Fe, Ga, Ge, In, Nb, Ni, Pd, Pt, Rh, Ru, Se, Si, Ta, Tb, Ti, V, Y, Zn</Symbol>		<Names>aluminium, gold, barium, copper, iron, gallium, germanium, indium, niobium, nickel, palladium, platinum, rhodium, ruthenium, selenium, silicon, tantalum, terbium, titanium, vanadium, yttrium, zinc</Names>	</objects>	<objects>	<Obj>Sink</Obj>		<Descr>The stainless steel sink contains iron which comes from hematite, chromium from the mineral chromite, and nickel from pentlandite. Niobium is used also in the manufacture of stainless steel. Ytterbium improves the strength of stainless steel.</Descr>		<Symbol>Cr, Fe, Nb, Ni, Yb</Symbol>		<Names>chromium, iron, niobium, nickel, ytterbium</Names>	</objects>	<objects>	<Obj>Plates</Obj>		<Descr>Plates are made of clays or glass. If they have colourful designs these come from pigments. Pigments can contain iron (blue-green colour, dark brown or black, antimony (yellow), copper (bright green) and cobalt (bright blue). Iron comes from hematite, antimony from stibnite, copper from chalcopyrite, and cobalt from cobaltite.</Descr>		<Symbol>Fe, Co, Cu, Sb</Symbol>		<Names>iron, cobalt, copper, antimony</Names>	</objects>	<objects>	<Obj>Cutlery</Obj>		<Descr>Stainless steel cutlery contains iron from hematite, chromium from the mineral chromite, and nickel from pentlandite. Niobium is used also in the manufacture of stainless steel. Silver is often used in the manufacture of cutlery. Silver is often found in deposits of the lead mineral galena or with gold. Technetium, a by-product of uranium decay, is an anticorrosive in steels.</Descr>		<Symbol>Ag, Cr, Fe, Nb, Ni, Tc</Symbol>		<Names>silver, chromium, iron, niobium, nickel, technetium</Names>	</objects>	<objects>	<Obj>Saucepans</Obj>		<Descr>The stainless steel pot on the stove contains iron from hematite, chromium from the mineral chromite, and nickel from pentlandite. Niobium is used also in the manufacture of stainless steel. Technetium, a by-product of uranium decay, is an anticorrosive in steels.</Descr>		<Symbol>Cr, Fe, Nb, Ni, Tc</Symbol>		<Names>chromium, iron, niobium, nickel, technetium</Names>	</objects>	<objects>	<Obj>Camera</Obj>		<Descr>The camera body is made from aluminium or iron, and the lens contains silicon and other elements like tantalum create a high refractive index, an important function of the camera lens. If the camera uses film there will be silver present.</Descr>		<Symbol>Ac, Cs, Po, Ta, Fe, Al, Ag</Symbol>		<Names>actinium, caesium, polonium, tantalum, iron, aluminium, silver</Names>	</objects>	<objects>	<Obj>Extinguisher</Obj>		<Descr>Bismuth is used in fire extinguishers. This element is found in the minerals bismite, bismuthinite, and bismutite. The steel container of fire extinguishers contains iron, carbon, copper, manganese, phosphorus and silicon.</Descr>		<Symbol>Bi, Cu, Fe, Mn</Symbol>		<Names>bismuth, copper, iron, manganese</Names>	</objects>	<objects>	<Obj>Pen</Obj>		<Descr>Ballpoint pens have a small rotating ball made of brass, steel or tungsten carbide to disperse ink as you write. Osmium and iridium help to make the ball stronger. Brass is an alloy of copper and zinc. The ink in the pen also contains metals. Black ink is derived from carbon. Coloured inks are inorganic compounds of chromium (yellow, green, and orange), molybdenum (orange), cadmium (red and yellow), and iron (blue). Molybdenum is extracted from molybdenite. Cadmium can be extracted from Greenockite, a sulfide mineral. Sphalerite is a common sulfide mineral of zinc.</Descr>		<Symbol>Cd, Cr, Cu, Fe, Ir, Mo, Os, W, Zn</Symbol>		<Names>cadmium, chromium, copper, iron, iridium, molybdenum, osmium, tungsten, zinc</Names>	</objects>	<objects>	<Obj>Gloves</Obj>		<Descr>Lithium used in the manufacture of rubber gloves comes from the mineral spodumene.</Descr>		<Symbol>Li</Symbol>		<Names>Lithium</Names>	</objects>	<objects>	<Obj>Bait</Obj>		<Descr>Important ingredients in ant baits include thallium and boron. The most common sources of boron are tourmaline, borax and kernite.</Descr>		<Symbol>Tl</Symbol>		<Names>thallium</Names>	</objects>	<objects>	<Obj>Cleaner</Obj>		<Descr>The abrasive part of this cleanser is silica, which contains silicon.</Descr>		<Symbol>Si</Symbol>		<Names>silicon</Names>	</objects>	<objects>	<Obj>Toaster</Obj>		<Descr>The stainless steel toaster contains iron from hematite, chromium from the mineral chromite, and nickel from pentlandite. The lead in the toaster comes from galena. The copper in the toaster is extracted from chalcopyrite.</Descr>		<Symbol>Cr, Cu, Fe, Ni, Pb</Symbol>		<Names>chromium, copper, iron, nickel, lead</Names>	</objects>	<objects>	<Obj>Phone</Obj>		<Descr>Components within the telephone contain copper, aluminium, nickel, tin, silicon and gold.</Descr>		<Symbol>Al, Au, Cu, Fe, Ni, Si, Sn</Symbol>		<Names>aluminium, gold, copper, iron, nickel, silicon, tin</Names>	</objects>	<objects>	<Obj>Stove</Obj>		<Descr>The stainless steel parts of the stove contain iron from hematite, chromium from the mineral chromite, and nickel from pentlandite. The lead in the stove comes from galena. The copper in the stove is extracted from chalcopyrite. Mercury used in the thermometer is obtained from cinnabar, a mercury sulphide. The thermocouple in the oven contains rhenium.</Descr>		<Symbol>Al, Au, Cu, Fe, Ni, Si, Sn, La, Ce, Pr, Nd, Pm, Sm, Eu, Gd, Tb, Dy, Ho, Er, Tm, Yb, Re</Symbol>		<Names>aluminium, gold, copper, iron, nickel, silicon, tin, lanthanum, cerium, praseodymium, neodynium, promethium, samarium, europium, gadolinium, terbium, dysprosium, holmium, erbium, thulium, ytterbium, rhenium</Names>	</objects>	<objects>	<Obj>Microwave</Obj>		<Descr>The interior of microwave ovens is made from aluminium which is extracted from bauxite. This is because aluminium does not absorb many microwaves. Microwave ovens also have copper wiring, with the copper coming from chalcopyrite. The main part of the oven is made from steel that contains iron, carbon, copper, manganese, phosphorus and silicon.</Descr>		<Symbol>Al, Cu, Fe, Mn</Symbol>		<Names>aluminium, copper, iron, manganese</Names>	</objects>	<objects>	<Obj>Window</Obj>		<Descr>The aluminium in the window frame comes from bauxite. The glass contains silicon derived from quartz.</Descr>		<Symbol>Al, Si</Symbol>		<Names>aluminium, silicon</Names>	</objects>	<objects>	<Obj>Glass</Obj>		<Descr>Glass is made from silicon, found in the mineral silica.</Descr>		<Symbol>Si</Symbol>		<Names>silicon</Names>	</objects>	<objects>	<Obj>Dishwasher</Obj>		<Descr>The stainless steel parts of the dishwasher contain iron from hematite, chromium from the mineral chromite, and nickel from pentlandite. The lead in the dishwasher comes from galena. The copper in the dishwasher is extracted from chalcopyrite.</Descr>		<Symbol>Cr, Cu, Fe, Ni, Pb</Symbol>		<Names>chromium, copper, iron, nickel, lead</Names>	</objects>	<objects>	<Obj>Salt and Pepper shakers</Obj>		<Descr>The stainless steel salt and pepper shakers contain iron which comes from hematite, chromium from the mineral chromite, and nickel from pentlandite. The salt is derived from the mineral halite, which is sodium chloride.</Descr>		<Symbol>Cr, Fe, Na, Ni</Symbol>		<Names>chromium, iron, sodium, nickel</Names>	</objects>	<objects>	<Obj>Blender</Obj>		<Descr>The stainless steel blender contains iron from hematite, chromium from the mineral chromite, and nickel from pentlandite. The lead in the blender comes from galena. The copper in the blender is extracted from chalcopyrite.</Descr>		<Symbol>Cr, Cu, Fe, Ni, Pb</Symbol>		<Names>chromium, copper, iron, nickel, lead</Names>	</objects>	<objects>	<Obj>Magnet</Obj>		<Descr>The fridge magnets are made of iron from hematite. They may also include neodymium, a rare earth element obtained from pegmatite.</Descr>		<Symbol>Fe, Lu, La, Ce, Pr, Nd, Pm, Sm, Eu, Gd, Tb, Dy, Ho, Er, Tm, Yb</Symbol>		<Names>iron, lutetium, lanthanum, cerium, praseodymium, neodynium, promethium, samarium, europium, gadolinium, terbium, dysprosium, holmium, erbium, thulium, ytterbium</Names>	</objects>	<objects>	<Obj>Coffee Pot</Obj>		<Descr>The stainless steel coffee maker contains iron from hematite, chromium from the mineral chromite, and nickel from pentlandite. The tube where the water is heated is made from aluminium, which was extracted from bauxite.</Descr>		<Symbol>Al, Cr, Fe, Ni</Symbol>		<Names>aluminium, chromium, iron, nickel</Names>	</objects>	<objects>		<Obj>Lamp</Obj>		<Descr>The light globe will contain glass made from silica Si), soda ash (Na), lime (Ca), coal and salt. The filament is tungsten. The wires into the filament contain copper and nickel. Molybdenum wires support the lead-in wires. The wires in the glass are made of a combination of nickel-iron alloy with a copper sleeve. There is a fuse made of nickel, manganese, copper and/or silicon alloys. The base is made of brass (Cu and Zn).	If the globe is fluorescent it will contain Beryllium and germanium.</Descr>		<Symbol>Si, Na, Ca, W, Cu, Ni, Mo, Mn, Zn, Be, Ge</Symbol>		<Names>silicon, sodium, calcium, tungsten, copper, nickel, molybdenum, manganese, zinc, beryllium, germanium</Names>	</objects></kitchen>